JOE: The level of an individual’s autism
disorder can be a factor in making a
decision about education, as those who are
high functioning may fit more easily into
mainstream schools but may not get that
extra attention they might thrive from.
Some mainstream schools have centres
providing specialist support incorporated
into them, this can provide support
from trained staff, such as learning
in small groups and therapies,
and a calm setting to retreat to.
BETH: Before parents choose a school,
they should check up on what extra
facilities are available such as extra
teaching support, different approaches
to teaching and separate lessons.
This may be all a child with autism may
need, but for some this may not be enough.
There are different benefits and
challenges to all of these types of
education, such as inclusion and good
practice, that are crucial for enabling
children on the autism spectrum to be
educated to their greatest potential.
JOE: Once an individual with autism
has progressed through education, they
are going to have to gain employment
if they are going to be able to become
more independent and self-sufficient.
Those who find employment may not always
be able to maintain this due to their
disorders and associated problems.
However, if employers are more
aware of the issues and work with
occupational health professionals
often employers can benefit greatly
from employees on the spectrum.
BETH: The nature of their disorder in
some high functioning individuals with
autism can make certain professions
ideal, such as using finely tuned
special interests such as maths
abilities in finance and banking.
Many local initiatives are now evolving,
helping companies to see an individual
with autism as an asset to their
company rather than having a disability.
JOE: Some individuals with autism can
struggle to get access to services as
they can be very articulate and seem
to show that they don’t need support
or the help of different services.
BETH: They therefore can be blocked
from some social care services
or from learning disability or
mental health specific services.
Social care assessors can sometimes
lack sufficient awareness of autism to
identify an individual’s specific needs.
JOE: To overcome any of these potential
effects an individual with autism
and their family, have more hurdles
to deal with on top of the nature of
their disorder, and this only make
life more difficult at every stage.